

Alaric D'Souza MD/PhD candidate



714-926-4569



alaricdsouza.github.io



orcid: 0000-0002-8744-8136



alaric.dsouza@wustl.edu

About me ——

Alaric is a final year MD/PhD student at Washington University in St. Louis. He completed his Computational and Systems Biology dissertation research on Microbial Ecology and antibiotic resistance genes in the Dantas Lab. In Fall 2021, Alaric will apply to Pediatrics residencies, with the intention of specializing in Infectious Diseases via a Physician Scientist Training Program. After finishing his training, Alaric hopes to lead his own research group studying microbial communities and host-pathogen interactions.

Skills -

Software Packages

Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, EndNote, LaTeX, Microsoft Office

Programming Languages

Python, R, Bash, Wolfram

Mathematica

Languages English (native)

Hindi (beginner)

Computer Hardware, Machining and Fabrication, Welding

research interests

Microbial ecology, bacterial genomics, and antibiotic resistance.

education

2014-pres. MD candidate Washington University in St. Louis

M4 with USMLE STEP exams complete

2016-20 Dantas Lab, Washington University in St. Louis

Computational and Systems Biology

2010-14 Yale University

Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

research and work experience

2016-20 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis Doctoral Candidate | Ecology of hospital built environment bacteria and

infant gut microbiota.

2015 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis

Rotation Student | Autologous Fecal Microbial Transplant Analysis

2012-14 Powell Lab Undergraduate Researcher | Foraging behavior of Aedes aegypti

mosquitoes.

2013 Gagneux Lab Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute Undergraduate Researcher | Antibiotic resistance and mutation rates in

Mycobacterium tuberculosis.

2012 Schlesinger Lab The Ohio State University Undergraduate Researcher | Macrophage receptor signaling for Mycobacterium tuberculosis phagosome lysosome fusion escape.

2011 Seva Dhan Mumbai, India

Summer Intern | Treatment of alcoholics and drug addicts. 2011 Course Consulting Canyon High School

Consultant | Course design for AP Psychology and IB Theory of Knowl-

edge.

Mentee of Dr. P.S. Wijewarnasuriya 2009 Army Research Labs Summer Intern | Semiconductor photoresist optimization for infrared

detectors.

publications

* authors contributed equally

2021 Destination shapes antibiotic resistance gene acquisitions, abundance increases, and diversity changes in Dutch travelers.

D'Souza AW*, Boolchandani M*, Patel S, Galazzo G, Hattem J, Arcilla M,

Melles D, Jong M, Schultsz C, Dantas G, Penders J Genome Medicine | 10.1186/s13073-021-00893-z

2021 Manure microbial communities and resistance profiles reconfigure after transition to manure pits and differ from fertilized field soil

> Sukhum K, Vargas R, D'Souza AW, Boolchandani M, Patel S, Kesaraju A, Walljasper G, Hedge H, Ye Z, Valenzuela R, Gunderson P, Bendixsen C,

Dantas G, Shukla S

mBio | 10.1128/mBio.00798-21

2020 Environmental remodeling of human gut microbiota and antibiotic re-

sistome in livestock farms

Sun J*, Liao XP*, D'Souza AW*, Boolchandani M*, Li SH*, Cheng K, Martinez JL, Li L, Feng YJ, Fang LX, Huang T, Xia J, Yu Y, Zhou YF, Sun YX, Deng XB, Zeng ZL, Jiang HX, Fang BH, Tang YZ, Lian XL, Zhang RM, Fang ZW, Yan QL, Dantas G, Liu YH

Nature Communications | 10.1038/s41467-020-15222-y

2019 Genomic characterization of antibiotic resistant Escherichia coli isolated from domestic chickens in Pakistan Rafique M*, Potter RF*, Ferreiro A, Wallace MA, Rahim A, Malik AA, Siddique N, Abbas MA, D'Souza AW, Burnham CD, Ali N, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology | 10.3389/fmicb.2019.03052 2019 Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and α -diversity but decreases β -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants. D'Souza AW*, Moodley-Govender E*, Berla B, Kelkar T, Wang B, Sun X, Daniels B, Coutsoudis A, Trehan I, Dantas G Clinical Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/cid/ciz1186 2019 Breakpoint beware: reliance on historical breakpoints for Enterobacteriaceae leads to discrepancies in interpretation of susceptibility testing for carbapenems and cephalosporins and gaps in detection of carbapenem-resistant organisms. Yarbrough ML, Wallace MA, Potter RF, D'Souza AW, Dantas G, Burnham CD European Journal of Clinical Microbiology & Infectious Diseases | 10.1007/s10096-019-03711-y Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. 2019 D'Souza AW*, Potter RF*, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Sun X, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Nature Communications | 10.1038/s41467-019-12563-1 2019 Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of linezolid resistant Enterococcus faecium from the USA and Wardenburg K*, Potter R*, D'Souza AW, Hussain T, Wallace M, Andleeb A, Burnham CA, Dantas G Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | 10.1093/jac/dkz367 Sequencing-based methods and resources to study antimicrobial resistance. 2019 Boolchandani M*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G Nature Reviews Genetics | 10.1038/s41576-019-0108-4 2018 Infant diet and maternal gestational weight gain predict early metabolic maturation of gut microbiomes. Baumann-Dudenhoeffer AM, D'Souza AW, Tarr PI, Warner BB, Dantas G Nature Medicine | 10.1038/s41591-018-0216-2 2018 Superficieibacter electus gen. nov., sp. nov., an Extended-Spectrum β -Lactamase Possessing Member of the Enterobacteriaceae Family, Isolated From Intensive Care Unit Surfaces. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Beatty W, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology | 10.3389/fmicb.2018.01629 2017 Draft Genome Sequence of the blaOXA-436- and blaNDM-1-Harboring Shewanella putrefaciens SA70 Isolate. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Genome Announcements | 10.1128/genomeA.00644-17 2016 The rapid spread of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G *Drug Resistance Updates* | 10.1016/j.drup.2016.09.002 2014 Malignant cancer and invasive placentation: A case for positive pleiotropy between endometrial and malignancy phenotypes. D'Souza AW and Wagner GP Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health | 10.1093/emph/eou022 published abstracts 2021 Microbiome and immune disruption accompany mouse death in a gnotobiotic mouse model of neonatal sepsis Schwartz D, Wardenburg K, Shalon N, Ning J, Crofts T, D?Souza A, Robinson J, Henderson J, Warner B, Tarr P, Dantas G Journal of the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society | 10.1093/jpids/piab031.010 2020 The Gut Microbiome and Resistome of Healthy Volunteers are Restructured After Short Courses of Antibiotics Anthony W, Sukhum K, Cass C, Reske K, Seiler S, Hink T, Coon C, D'Souza A, Wang B, Sun S, Dubberke E,

Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Kwon JH

2017

Infection Control & Hospital Epidemiology | 10.1017/ice.2020.476

Open Forum Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/ofid/ofx163.245

Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Multidrug-resistant Organism Contamination in the US and Pakistan Kwon JH, D'Souza A, Potter R, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Andleeb S, Burnham C-A, Dantas G

2015 Autologous Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Strategy to Prevent Colonization With Multidrug-Resistant

Organisms Following Antimicrobial Therapy

Bulow C, D'Souza A, Hink T, Wallace M, Reske K, Sun X, Kwon JH, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Dubberke E Open Forum Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/ofid/ofv133.479

invited talks

2021	An exploration of Emergency Department turnaround time data WUSTL Clinical Informatics Seminar
2021	Total thyroidectomy in a 15 yo F with familial adenomatous polyposis WUSTL GI Seminar
2021	Angiomyolipoma in a 9 yo F with tuberous sclerosis WUSTL Pathology Seminar
2020	16S rRNA gene sequencing in bacterial endocarditis WUSTL Lab Medicine Seminar
2019	Effects of antibiotic prophylaxis on the HIV-exposed uninfected infant gut microbiome WUSTL MSTP Work in Progress Seminar
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Microbiology Department Seminar
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology Micro
2017	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan CSB-MMMP-PMB Interdepartmental Retreat
2017	Multidrug resistant organisms on hospital surfaces in the United States and Pakistan Computational and Systems Biology Retreat
2017	Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the United States and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology Micro
2017	Effects of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the microbiomes of HIV- infants born to HIV+ mothers WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences
2017	Antibiotic Resistance: a growing public health crisis WUSTL Institute of Public Health
2013	Drop Team and Rayleigh-Taylor instability Canyon High School AP biology class
2012	Mannose Receptor Signaling SUCCESS

patents

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics Conference

posters	
2019	Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. IMM/MICRO Mini WIP
2019	Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and α -diversity but decreases β -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants. American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe
2019	Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the US and Pakistan NIAID/IDSA Infectious Diseases Research Careers Meeting
2018	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan American Physician Scientist Association (APSA) Midwest meeting
2018	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

2018	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe
2017	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe
2017	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan 5th annual Global Health & Infectious Disease Conference
2014	Invasive populations of <i>Aedes aegypti</i> in Central California Yale Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Poster Session
2013	The genetics of foraging behavior in <i>Aedes aegypti</i> Cell Symposia: Genes, Circuits, and Behavior
2012	Mannose receptor signaling linking spleen tyrosine kinase and MAP kinase p38 in human macrophages The Ohio State University SUCCESS program
2009	Relationship of spinning time and speed to photoresist thickness on semiconductor wafers Army Research Labs: Science and Engineering Apprentice Program
awards	

2021	Gold Humanism Honor Society Inductee
2020	Spencer T. and Ann W. Olin Fellow
2017-18	Burroughs Wellcome Fund, Institutional Program Unifying Population and Laboratory-Based Sciences
2016	BioEnterpreneurship Core Bench to Business Competition
2015	IDEA Labs Demo Day Finalist
2013	Alan S. Tetelman Fellowship for International Research in the Sciences
2013	Paul K. and Evelyn Elizabeth Cook Richter Fellowship
2012	CBC Spouses Cheerios Brand Health Initiative Scholarship
2011	CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship
2010	CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship

activities and leadership			
2019-pres.	Volunteer Seeing patients as a medical student volunteer for the free clinic	Saturday Neighborhood Health Clinic	
2014-pres.	Yale Admissions Interviewer Interviewer for Yale College admissions of prospective undergraduate st	Yale Alumni Schools Committee udents	
2015-17	Physicians for Human Rights Co-President of club focusing on human rights and political issues that relate to medicine, including health-care for prisoner, refugees, and underserved communities		
2014-17	Store-Easy Washington University in St. Louis - Sling Health Company seeking to improve manual wheelchair storage in automobiles		
2012-14	Drop Team Undergraduate research team selected by NASA to conduct fluid mechai	Yale University nics research in zero-gravity	
2012-14	Splash at Yale Undergraduate group teaching short courses to middle and high school	Yale University students	
2011-14	Big Sib Mentor to freshman students at Yale University	Yale University - Pierson College	

teaching

3	
2017-20	Computational Teaching Assistant Fundamentals of Biostatistics Washington University in St. Louis
2017-20	Graduate Mentor Visiting scholars, rotation students, and undergraduates Dantas Lab
2017	Teaching Assistant Microbes and Pathogenesis Washington University in St. Louis
2017	Graduate Mentor IPH Summer Program Washington University in St. Louis
2016	Graduate Mentor Eureka Program Washington University in St. Louis
2013-14	Lecturer Origins of Life Yale Splash
2011-14	Lecturer The Science of Ice Cream Yale Splash

professional memberships

2020-pres. Gold Humanism Honor Society

2019-pres. Infectious Diseases Society of America2016-pres. American Society for Microbiology